Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we're going to be
learning about enthalpy and stoichiometry.
Now when it comes to chemical reactions,
what is one of the most important
concepts is that when a reaction is
happening, bonds are being broken
and new bonds are being formed.
And depending on your course, you
will have to do different types of
calculations, maybe using thermochemistry
tables, maybe just using stoichiometry.
To in order to calculate different
values of heat or mass or moles
now, why is this so important?
It's once again is that all chemical
reactions they absorb or release
heat Because energy is transferred
within a chemical reaction, right?
If you think of the Sun shining above
it is transferring heat to all kinds of
different plants and things around, right?
So we think of plants photosynthesis
occurring because it's absorbing
that UV light which is energy
to help those reactions happen
Heat is always transferred.
Whether something feels cold or whether
something feels hot, you are able
to actually calculate the number of
joules or energy that's being released.
So this video specifically will look
at the stoichiometry, meaning that
we have to understand how to use a
balanced chemical reaction to be able
to actually determine the stoichiometry.
We will be calculating the masses,
meaning that we're going to be
using molar mass as a component.
And we're going to be using the mole to
mole ratios that come with terminology
found within the heat of, or within
our enthalpy of our reaction here.
So we're going to be focusing on delta
H, how to calculate that, and let's
take a look at some of the different
calculations and what this involves.
The first thing that we have to
make sure we understand as well is
knowing our key vocabulary and terms.
Right, you don't want to go into
your first exam or your homework,
see all these new terms that
you just don't recognize, right?
You need to be able to understand
what do they represent.
The first thing is understanding the
different types of heat reactions,
which is exothermic and endothermic.
Exothermic is all about
when we're referring to how
much heat is being released.
Or energy is released, meaning
it's coming out, right?
It's being produced as a result.
It feels really hot when we have
something is exothermic, meaning that
when we look at, let's say a chemical
reaction, we'll see that, okay, A is
going to be right reactants to products
and it's generating heat as a product.
So that's really important to realize heat
is a product when it comes to exothermic.
Okay.
So, you might also have to look at energy
diagrams like the one shown here, where
if I have, let's say, two reactants, so
I have hydrogen and chlorine gas, they're
combining together, and as a result, when
that happens, they're going to make HCl.
Now, in order for this reaction to happen,
you can see that heat is a product, right?
So it's, it takes, it's going
to release 185 kilojoules.
So the way that we can represent
that is using energy curves
like the one shown here.
Where essentially, if I have my
reactants, it's going to, the reaction
is going to start, and then all of a
sudden it's going to release a ton of
energy when the products are formed.
And that's the key thing, right?
There's energy required,
it's being released.
So when you see that there's less energy
in the products, That means that you
release and this is favorable, right?
So this is spontaneous when this
happens Exothermic is favorable.
So the way that we show the Delta H the
reaction is we're simply just reading
what's in this formula now being that we
have 185 in the products is exothermic.
We're going to represent that
using a negative value for XO.
So XO is negative.
So when we write this and say, Hey,
Delta H, we're going to put negative
185 kilojoules is going to be our
answer here for how to represent that.
And that's going to be 185 kilojoules.
per mole.
All right, so that's going to be our
units, and we're going to tell you how
many moles that is what's all going to be.
And as you can see too, heat is a
product, which is very important.
Let's look at endothermic.
Absorbing heat.
Heat is required to make this happen.
So being that heat is required here
for the reaction to occur, we need to
absorb it or it's not going to happen.
Right?
So in order for like photosynthesis
to occur for plants to produce
oxygen, they need to absorb
sunlight for that to happen.
So that's an example of endothermic
because it to absorb energy.
Now, when we're looking at these
and trying to understand, all
right, how can we represent it?
Well, generally the reactants
by themselves, they are happy.
They actually don't have the urge to
react when it's an endothermic process.
There needs to be something
to kind of kick it off in
order for it for it to occur.
So if you give it energy, let's say
if you have nitrogen, oxygen, gas,
let's say in the upper atmosphere.
And it's absorbing UV rays from the
sun, and they combine together at
the right time, well then you can
actually have it where they can form.
Nitrogen monoxide as a product, which
is a very, um, global warming gas or
a dangerous gas, meaning that energy
had to be absorbed for that to happen.
It doesn't occur by itself.
It's not spontaneous.
It needs energy to happen.
All right.
So when we have that, you can
see that it's the energy is
written as a reactant here, right?
It's plus 180 kJ in the reactants.
Meaning that we are going to write this
as a positive this time and it's going
to be a hundred and eighty kilojoules
per mole is going to be our reactant.
Okay, so that's step one.
What else can we get from looking
at these different values?
Next part is how to use reaction
enthalpy as a conversion factor,
which is generally the most important
part of using this in stoichiometry.
Stoichiometry is just word
problems and dimensional analysis
wrapped up in chemical reactions.
So when we're using this, it's all
about the amount of thermal energy
that's absorbed or released by a
chemical reaction and this be specific.
This is at a constant pressure.
So if you're trying to use this in terms
of maybe more general chemistry to type
calculations, you're going to need a
different formula to calculate these.
Um, you can still use these, but it might
be a different process for your course.
So keep that in mind.
Um, now when we are using these,
these are conversion factors.
So what you need to do is be
able to read a chemical formula.
It might look like the one here.
So this is a combustion reaction where
we have propane reacting with oxygen gas.
So propane is C3H8.
And it's going to burn
and make CO2 and water.
Now, as you can see above, I have the
delta H of the reaction listed, and it
says that it's negative 2044 kilojoules.
So what can you learn from that?
Well, the first thing is, is that,
okay, well that's exothermic because
it is a negative symbol that's here.
The next thing is that
technically the heat could be
written as a product as well.
So there could be two different
ways that this can be illustrated.
So let's say if I kind of, uh,
if I make the chemical formula a
little smaller, this could also be
illustrated in the actual chemical
reaction as a product as well.
So we could say plus 2044
kilojoules written inside.
So there's two different ways that
the same information can be shown,
which is really important that
you're paying attention to signs.
And how it's being shown, if
energy is being given to you in the
problem, 99 percent of the time,
it's probably an enthalpy problem.
All right.
Now, what else can you get?
Well, being that we know that
this is negative 2044 kilojoules,
this is for every mole.
All right.
So if you remember from before it
was negative 2044 kilojoules, and
this was over moles, but what number
of moles, how can you relate it to?
Well, it's all related to the
chemical equation that's above.
We can actually relate it to
the number for all the different
coefficients that are in the problem.
So for example, we can
relate that to any of these.
So if I say negative 2044
kilojoules is released for every
one mole of C3H8 that is burned.
Okay.
Now, where did I get the one mole?
Well, that's because, essentially,
we have a 1 that's in front
of C3H8, so we can use that.
Um, another example is, let's say
if I use the 5O2, well, if I have 5
moles of O2, that's also equivalent
to negative 2044 kilojoules of
energy released, because this is a
complete balanced chemical equation.
That's the important thing.
It has to be balanced.
So we could also do this
with the products too.
We could say, hey, I have three
moles of CO2, and that's going to
be also equivalent to, hey, you
might have guessed it, negative
2044 kilojoules for this reaction.
Keep that in mind.
This reaction, every reaction is going to
have a slightly different energy value.
And the last one is, well, if I
have four moles of water, I can also
relate that to four moles of H2O.
all over, once again, you
might've guessed it, negative 2044
kilojoules per four moles of water.
So all of these terms, all four
of them, are available to you.
Now, which one do you use?
It depends on the problem
that's being presented to you.
So if you're being given, let's
say the mass of propane, you would
use the first term over here.
If you were given, let's say
maybe the mass or moles of oxygen,
you would use the middle one.
And so forth.
You have to read the problem
carefully, which we're going
to show in our next example.
All right, so let's look at
the tips and tricks of how
to solve these word problems.
How much heat is involved
with the combustion of 1.
18 times 10 to the 4 grams of propane?
And we have the same balanced
chemical equation that we
had in the previous example.
So what exactly do we need to do here?
Well, being that, we gotta first
highlight what information we were given
in our problem, and we can see that,
hey, we were given the exact mass of
propane that was used in this reaction.
So we had propane, we
are going to burn it.
Now the thing that is being asked of
us, or what is our desire, is that we
want to know how much heat there is.
So how exactly can we do it?
Um, and we're also given
what the delta H is as well.
So we have a couple different E values
that are very important here, which we
can try to use to figure out what the
different pieces of information are.
So in this problem, what we need to do
is kind of map it out for ourselves.
We want to start with our grams, right?
So as always, you want to write out
all the little pieces of information
you're given, which first thing is, is
your desired, or is your given terms.
Right?
So we have 1.
18 times 10 to the 4 grams, which
is a term that's by itself, right?
You always want to start with
a term that's not a fraction
because it's easier to start with.
We're going to write out our T
table, which what all a T table
is, is the equivalent of fractions
multiplying by each other.
So top and bottom is your fraction.
So what we need to first do is we
need to cancel out grams and get two
moles because what we need to use.
is our enthalpy value, right?
Which was kilojoules per mole, right?
We can relate that to
our chemical equation.
So being that this first part is
grams, and it's grams of propane,
so we should label that What we are
going to do is essentially cancel this
out with our molar mass of propane.
So using molar mass to do that,
what we need to do is essentially
calculate and look up all of our
values from our periodic table.
So being that I have carbon and
hydrogen conveniently over here,
we are going to take three carbons,
add that to eight hydrogens, Add it
all together, and we will get 44.
097 grams per mole for our molar mass.
Now, when we use that, we are
going to plug that in and cancel
our units, so grams is on bottom.
Notice how they're opposite of one
another, just like we've done in the past.
And this is always equivalent
to one mole of C3H8.
Now, being that our goal is always the
mole, we got it there, which is fantastic.
What we are going to now do
is need to, we need to convert
from moles to energy, right?
Because we want to know how
much heat, what is the number
of kilojoules that's desired.
And what you need to now do is the
equation has to be balanced for you to
be able to do the step we showed earlier.
Right, which we have up above.
We have the balanced chemical
equation all the way up top here.
So what we can now relate to is being
that we started with propane and what
we can see is is that there's one mole
of C3H8 from our balanced chemical
formula And what is that equivalent to?
It's at negative 2044 kilojoules, right?
So just like so.
Now, what we're going to now see
is that our units cancel, which is
great, and we have it in kilojoules
of C3H8 for the energy of that.
And what we are going to do is we take 1.
18 times 10 to the 4, times that
by 1, times that by negative 2044,
and we're going to divide it by 44.
097, and then divide that answer by
1, and you will get your final answer.
So when you put this in your
calculator what you should be
getting is five or five, four,
six, nine, five, eight kilojoules.
Okay, so it's a very, very large number.
Typically with these we always
want to round them to sig figs and
put them in scientific notation.
So we can see that, hey, we're going
to be moving this decimal five times,
um, and we want to round it to three
sig figs because we started with three
sig figs at the very, very beginning.
So what are we going to have in the end
is negative 5, 000, or sorry, negative 5.
47 times 10 to the 5th kilojoules is
your final answer for this problem.
So this is how you can do, how
you can find the amount of energy.
Now our last example is going to
be find how the amount of mass
that was either created or used
to make this amount of energy.
So we're going to do the backwards.
Let's take a look at our last problem.
Let's practice this problem.
So what we have is diboron trioxide,
which is a solid formed by the reaction
of igniting boron powder in oxygen gas.
And what it's telling you is that
we also have a delta H reaction
of negative 1273 kilojoules.
Now, and it's asking, how much
diboron trioxide did you start with
if 1690 kilojoules is released?
Assume di, assume a diboron
trioxide molar mass of 69.
62 grams per mole.
Okay, so these types of problems are
very, very difficult because we weren't
given the actual chemical equation.
We have to read this very, very carefully.
When doing it.
So the first thing that we are
going to do is that we are going
to balance our chemical equation.
Now what it says is that D boron trioxide,
so dye is two, so it's gonna be B two.
Trioxide is three, so B 2 0 3.
And it's a solid and it says it's formed.
Okay.
So formed means that it was
created or that it is a.
product in this case.
So we're going to write that on
the right hand side of the hour,
the, the, the arrow in this case.
Now it says we're going to ignite
boron powder with oxygen gas.
Boron is a solid, so that
just is, and it's a powder, so
that's going to be by itself.
Oxygen is a diatomic gas,
so we have that as well.
Now when we are balancing this,
we have to make sure that we
are using our coefficients.
So the first tip and trick I
always say is let's even the odds.
You can see that we have three
oxygens on the right, meaning
it's odd, so let's even it.
Uh, so we're going to add a two in front
of that to make six, which is even number.
I'll add a three in front of the
oxygen on the left hand side.
We evened the odds in this case,
and now what we can do is balance
our borons, and we see that we have
four and four on the left and right.
Now our next part of information
that was given to you was the delta
H of the reaction, which as we can
kind of see if we pull this out.
It was negative 1273 kilojoules,
which means that it's a product.
So we can also relate that to, um,
exactly being that it's talking
about diboron trioxide, we can
relate it to that value as well.
We can relate it to the number
of moles that is in the problem.
Being that it asks, okay, if we have
diboron trioxide, how much is there?
And we release this much energy.
What we are going to do is we are
going to define our conversion
term just like we did before.
And being that we have negative 1273
kilojoules, that's for every mole.
And, well, which mole are we going to use?
Well, the problem asks for B2O3.
So this is going to be equivalent
to for every two moles of B2O3.
And you can write this conversion term
for all the other values too, but they're
not, um, not important for this problem.
So when it comes to solving it,
we were given another value as
well, which was that you had
negative 1690 kilojoules of energy.
that was released.
So, which is a given term, right?
You want to start with that because
it's by itself, it's not a fraction.
Um, versus the other value that we have,
which is two moles of B2O3 is equivalent
to that six, that 12, 973 kilojoules.
This term can be flipped
one way or another.
So you don't know which one to start with.
If you choose wrongly, your units are
going to be flipped and it could lead
to confusion when you're at the end.
But the value that's on the left
hand side over here, that can
only, you can't flip it, right?
It's, it's easy the way it is.
We can just start with that.
So we're going to start there and we need
to use the balanced chemical equation.
So what we're going to do is
essentially cancel our units.
So we'll start with negative 1270.
And now we're, we need
to cancel out kilojoules.
So how can we exactly.
do that, well, we need to
have kilojoules on the bottom.
So what we can use is this term
on the top right here, and kind
of plug this value in like so.
And now what we can see is,
hey, your kilojoules cancelled.
Fantastic.
That is what we want when we
are looking at these problems.
Now we have our units in
moles, so how can we get grams?
is we need to use the molar mass of
B2O3, which was given in the problem.
So earlier that said it was 69.
62 grams per mole.
So let's kind of write that up here
so we can write it in correctly.
So we had 69.
62 grams and that's equivalent
for every one mole of B2O3.
And now we can see our, once again,
our units are doing what they're
supposed to do, which is cancel.
And now we're left only with grams
of B2O3, which is what we want.
So when we are solving this, we're
going to multiply everything on top and
then divide by what's on the bottom.
So we'll take negative 1690,
times that by 2, times that by 69.
62, and then divide by negative 1273.
And what we are going
to get, you'll get 184.
85 grams of B2O3, but we need to round
it to the correct number of sig figs.
We have 4 in this It's always being
based off what was given in the problem.
So as you can see, the number we started
with over here on the left is four.
So we'll round this slightly to 184.
9 grams of B2O3.
And that's how you solve These
are the boat the two types of
problems you can see with enthalpy.
It doesn't get any crazier than that.
Now the biggest thing you need to
make sure you do is you need to be
able to predict and balance problems.
If you need help with that, refer back to
my old videos on how to do that as well.
Okay.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope this video helped you.
Please let me know if you need any help.
Comment below if you do, and feel free
to, if this is your first time here,
hit that like and subscribe button.
Please keep helping the chemistry
channel grow, so that way it can
help more students just like you.
Thank you so much, and
I'll see you all later.
Bye now.